Allan B. Cunningham fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Allan B. Cunningham fonds
1961 - 1989
F-70
Q101243109
25 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Cunningham, Allan B.
Allan Cunningham was the first head of the History Department at Simon Fraser University. He obtained his BA degree from the University of Durham, and his MA and PhD degrees from the University of London. He was a Senior Research Fellow at Oxford University, when he accepted an appointment to SFU in 1964 to set up the History Department. Cunningham was a specialist in the Middle East and Arab-Israeli relations. A fellow of the Royal Geographic Society, the Royal Historical Society, and the Turkish Historical Society, Cunningham won a Guggenheim fellowship in 1979. He also served two terms as Dean of Arts during the early years of the University.
In addition to his career as a historian, Cunningham had a distinguished record as a spitfire pilot during World War II. He was also an accomplished painter and a well-known mountaineer. The Peak of the Brothers in the Andes is named after him and his brother, Frank Cunningham, who taught in SFU's geography department.
Allan Cunningham died in January 1988.
published
Full
Revised
Title of collection based on provenance.
Fonds consists primarily of the personal and professional correspondence of Allan Cunningham and a collection of historical essays about SFU.
The materials were arranged by the archivist.
The fonds was donated to the Archives by Allan Cunningham's wife, Jean, and Professor Bill Cleveland. Allan Cunningham's file on Africa and the Middle East was donated in 1997 by Professor Philip Stigger. Series Two was collected after Cunningham's death by Don Baird, the University Archivist at the time.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Consult the fonds of the Department of History, F 26. Also consult the Simon Fraser University Archives sound collection for two cassettes of Cunningham: an oral history (100/12/1) and an interview about foreign travel (100/8/82).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Correspondence, 1961 - 1975; F-70-1; 14 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of the personal and professional correspondence of Cunningham as well as miscellaneous documents apparently kept by Cunningham for their historical value in depicting the early years at SFU. Documents relate to such topics as the opening of the University, administrative and teaching matters, student protests, and the Friends of SFU (a U.S.-based fund-raising organization).
  - Correspondence, 1961 - 1964; F-70-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Correspondence, 1965; F-70-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1965; F-70-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1965; F-70-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Correspondence, 1966; F-70-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1966; F-70-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1967; F-70-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1967; F-70-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1968; F-70-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; F-70-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - African Studies, 1963 - 1973; F-70-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Opening Ceremonies, 1965; F-70-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - General Correspondence, 1965 - 1968; F-70-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 70-1)
  - Friends of SFU, 1968; F-70-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - Art Gallery, 1974 - 1975; F-70-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
- SFU Historical Essays, 1985 - 1989; F-70-2; 12 cm of textual records; All of the files in this series date from the 1980s, but the exact date of most of them (files 2-22) is not known.
  Cunningham asked several early faculty and other members of the SFU community to write down their recollections of the early years of the University. He had hoped that the University would produce a collection of essays to mark its 20th Anniversary. On the advice of an anonymous referee, the University decided against publishing the work. Cunningham considered other ways of producing the volume, but died before he could complete the project.
  Series includes rough drafts and final drafts of essays selected for the volume by Cunningham. Essays are listed by individual author. Series also includes correspondence about the project, essays not selected for the proposed volume (submissions by Cunningham, G. Bursill-Hall, T. Finlayson, M. Gibbons, E. Harden, A. Hean, D. Roberts, W. Vidauer, and L. Wilson), and a collection of historical essays by Archie MacKinnon.
  - Correspondence, 1985 - 1989; F-70-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
    August 2018: File folder retrieved and found to be empty.
  - Early drafts, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - I. Arthur Erickson, Designing Simon Fraser University, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - II. Mel Linden, Fond Remembrance, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - III Ron Baker, The Beginning, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - IV. Allan Cunningham, For Richer, For Poorer, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - V. Marilyn Cairns, A Strong Sense of Duty, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - VI. Thomas J. Mallinson, Brave New University, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - VII Sandy Dawson, The Originsof the Professional Development Program, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - VIII. Marg Sawyer, Unlikely Trail, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - IX. Gordon Elliott, An Eye-hole in the Frosted Windowpane, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - X. L. Johanne Stemo, The Lemondae Brigade, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XI. Heribert Adam, The Teaching of Political Literacy at SFU, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XII. Gregg Macdonald, Man in a Trenchcoat, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XIII. Richard Lester, A View from the Board, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XIV. Marg Sawyer, Search Committee, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XV. Frances Frazer, Jack Worthing on Burnaby Mountain, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XVI. Klaus E. Rieckhoff, On Trying to be Responsible and Responsive: A Physicist's Liaison with SFU, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XVII. J.M. Sandison, That Two-Handed Engine, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XVIII. Fulton Fisher, Change: Adaptive or Destrictive? A Plea for Principles, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - XIX. Ian Mugridge, Distance Education in the 1980s: A Personal View, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - Submissions not included in final draft, 1985; F-70-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 70-2)
  - An Adventure of Ideas: Reflections on the Beginnings of Simon Fraser University, A.R. MacKinnon, 1989; F-70-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 70-2)